Guide to the Al Stewart Collection MS 067
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Al Stewart Collection
1960s-2016
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Stewart, Albert C., 1919-2016
MS 067
12 Linear Feet
Al Stewart was a businessman and physicist who joined the faculty in the School of Business at WestConn in 1987 after a long career mostly at Union Carbide. The collection includes personal papers, objects, art and miscellanea from Stewart's estate.
Biographical / Historical
Albert C. Stewart was born on November 25, 1919. Stewart received his B.S. degree in chemistry from the University of Chicago in 1942. He was drafted into the U.S. Navy in 1945 and was among a select group of African American sea men trained as officers. Following his tour of duty, Stewart returned to the United States and enrolled at the University of Chicago. In 1948, he received his M.S. degree in chemistry; and, in 1949, he was commissioned as a second lieutenant into the U.S. Navy. Stewart earned his Ph.D. degree in chemistry from St. Louis University in 1951.
From 1949 to 1963, Stewart held teaching appointments at St. Louis University, Knoxville College, and John Carroll University where he taught chemistry and physics. In 1951, Stewart began his at the Union Carbide Corporation as a senior chemist in the nuclear division. In 1960, Stewart became the assistant director of research and held several leadership positions until his retirement in 1984.
After his retirement from Union Carbide Stewart began teaching at Western Connecticut University, where he also served as the associate dean in the Ancell School of Business. In 1999, Stewart became Professor Emeritus at Western Connecticut State University.
In 1966, Stewart received the University of Chicago Alumni Citation Award. Stewart was a member of a number of professional and academic societies, and has also served as an advisor, consultant and on the Board of Directors of several organizations, including U.S. Department of Commerce, NASA, and the Urban League, respectively.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged into two series, art and personal effects.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to the Archives in the fall of 2017 by the estate of Al Stewart.
Related Materials
The WCSU Miscellanea collection also includes Al Stewart materials.
Scope and Contents
The Stewart Collection consists of materials from his personal and professional life. The bulk of the collection contains art that Stewart had collected over the years that had been displayed in his home. It appears that most of that art was collected from Mexico around 1960.
The Stewart collection also contains some personal materials, such as awards and certificates, mostly from the 1970s through the 1990s.
Western Connecticut State University - History; Universities and colleges -- Faculty.; Art, African.; Art, Mexican--20th century.; Stewart, Albert C., 1919-2016
- Art
  - Vertical Sense (Sentido Vertical), Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 001)
  - Harmony (Armonia), Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 002)
  - Two Figures (Dos Figuras), Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 003)
  - Duality (Dualidad), Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 004)
  - No Longer Indifferent (Sin Indiferencia), Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 005)
  - Vision Of Companions (Vision de Compañeros), Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 006)
  - Red Rocks and People (Gente y Rocas Rojas), Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 007)
  - Harlequin, Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 008)
  - Angel, Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 009)
  - Virtuous Woman (Mujer Virtuosa), Herbert Hofmann-Ysenbourg, circa 1960 (Item 010)
  - Street Steps St. Thomas, Virgin Islands, 1958 (Item 011)
  - Fecundidad, 1956 (Item 012)
  - Christiansted, St. Croix, 1965 (Item 013)
  - [Seated Figure], 1960 (Item 014)
  - [Bride], 1959 (Item 015)
  - Mallorca, circa 1960 (Item 016)
  - [Multicolor Abstract], undated (Item 017)
  - A lasting friendship, by Joseph Raskob, 1961 (Item 018)
  - 4 African wood face carvings, undated (Item 019-022)
    General
    2 are by Kouadio
  - African bronze jewelry and bell (4 pieces), undated (Item 023-026)
  - Chez Maxime, undated (Box 1, Item 027)
- Personal effects
  - Portraits, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1 black and white; one color of Colleen and Al.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1970-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    Bowery Bank, WCSU, etc.
  - Oral history interview, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Books, 1976-2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Harlem Youth and Living Legends in Black
  - Patent, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Patent for an electric cell, # 3255045
  - Souvenir postcards and stamps, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Buffalo soldier stamp and portrait; Met postcards of Horace Pippin works.
  - Misc. Keepsakes, undated (Box 1, Item 1-4)
    Union Carbide paperweight, Buddha in a box, ball bearing and watercolor painting by Colleen Stewart.
  - Frederick Douglass bust, undated (Item 5.1)